Okay guys, welcome back to Gary's Economics. This week we've got something a little bit different for you.
We are going to show you a live recording of a speech I gave at Cambridge to kick off my book launch a couple of months ago.
I've got to be honest, if we've gotten around to this point, it means basically we have run out of videos.
And the reason for that is because I am currently on holiday cycling from Tokyo to Kagoshima in southwestern Japan.
All right. Listen, it's been a pretty mental year for me. I've been working really hard. The channel has grown a lot.
I've had a ton of publicity with the book. Trying to grow everything, trying to push things politically and it's been a lot of work.
And to be honest, I'm feeling a little bit creatively exhausted and, you know, we get a lot of support for this channel now.
I've got a manager and we've got Jack here, the videographer, but creatively it's still basically me who does the videos.
And with all the book and the interviews and the videos for the channel, I'm feeling a bit knackered and the election, all that nonsense.
So I've decided to get out of here, go back to Japan.
Those of you who have read the book when I lived in Japan for two years and I used to spend a lot of time in there before COVID.
So I've decided to take a little bit of a break, go and do this cycle that I've wanted to do for ages from Tokyo to to southwest Japan.
And I've tried my best to film videos to fill the gap, but I'm not sure we're going to be able to cover the whole time.
And we've scheduled this to be the last video before we go blank for a bit, maybe for part of August, before I come back for my holiday.
And this is a speech I gave at Robinson College in Cambridge.
It's a little bit more personal, a little bit more emotional than a lot of the stuff that I do.
Talking about sort of how I deal with sort of living in this economy where things get worse and worse and trying to stop it.
I think it's a really nice speech and I promised a room full of Scousers in Waterstones, Liverpool that I'd put it up on the YouTube at some point.
So hopefully they're still watching.
Unfortunately, there's a few problems with the sound quality, but since we've got a gap with no videos, I think it's worth watching.
I think it's really interesting. It's about 45 minutes long.
I hope you like it. I get a little bit emotional in it.
But after this, I think we'll probably have a gap of a few weeks before I come back in September and start shooting again.
So this will be it for me for a few weeks.
I'll be back and I hope you enjoy this last video. Thank you.
And also thanks for all of your help this year.
The growth has been really good and been really mental and hopefully we'll be able to have a little bit more political impact when I come back.
Thank you.
When I was contacted to do this lecture, they said, come to Robertson College, talk about economics, tell everyone why inequality is a problem.
And my agent said, that's perfect timing for your book launch, go do it.
So I said yes, and that's about a year ago now.
I didn't really think about it much.
Then they reached out to me a couple of months ago and they said, what do you want the title of your lecture to be?
And my first thought when they said that was, I don't really want to talk about economics anymore.
Let me explain to you why.
I've been talking about economics for a long time now.
13 years, 14 years, I've been having arguments about economics, trying to tell people inequality is a problem, inequality is a problem.
It's going to get worse, it's going to get worse, we need to do something.
And over the course of those 14 years, especially in the last year or two, what I've noticed is the arguments I've been having have been changing.
And more and more I start to think to myself that actually, we're not really arguing about economics at all.
See, when I first started saying inequality was a problem, I was working in a bank in Canary Wharf in London, and I was surrounded by millionaires of economics degrees.
And they would say to me, you can't tax wealth, you can't deal with inequality, because we need the rich to invest, to grow the economy.
The optimal rate of taxation in the first best of all possible worlds on capital is zero.
But nobody really says that to me anymore.
Okay, some people do say that sometimes in places like this, people say that, but nobody with that fancy economics degree says that to me anymore.
What people say to me now is, you can't tax the rich, you can't tax, they're too powerful.
You tax the rich, they'll leave and they'll go away and then we'll have nothing and then we'll be poor.
Or they say to me, it's impossible trying to deal with inequality.
Inequality is just the way things are, the rich are too powerful.
Why are you trying to stop them? You're wasting your time.
Or they say to me, why are you trying to stop inequality?
Why don't you just trade Bitcoin or foreign exchange on the internet?
That's the way to make everything better.
Or they say to me,
You know, the economy and society, it's like the cycles of nature.
Sometimes it's good and sometimes it's bad.
Sometimes it gets better and sometimes it gets worse.
So why are you trying to change things?
You can't fight the cycles of nature.
And the more I heard these arguments, the more I started to think,
we're not really arguing about the economy.
Increasingly, everybody knows it's getting worse and worse.
Really, hardly any real people think it's going to get better.
But I think people in their heart of hearts realise
that it just gets worse and worse from here.
And when they're saying to me,
why are you trying to fix things?
Often they're really saying to themselves,
I don't want to have to try to fix things.
And I started to feel like the real questions
that we're asking ourselves and each other
is not really,
is the economy broken?
It's what do you do?
What do you do when you live in a collapsing economy?
What do you do?
What should you do?
And what does it mean?
And more and more,
these are the questions that I hear
when I argue people about economics.
What do you do?
What should you do?
What does it mean?
And it got me thinking about my journey in economics.
I've been an economist for,
God, nearly 20 years now.
But I lived in an economy my whole life.
I grew up very poor,
so really poverty and a collapsing economy
is not new to me.
But it got me thinking,
what did I do?
What should I have done differently?
What does it all mean?
So I sent a memo back saying I wanted to talk about
what it means to be human in a collapsing economy.
And I'm going to talk a little bit about
what I think about my path.
And when I talk about that,
I want you to think about those three main questions.
What does it mean to live in a collapsing economy?
What do you do when the economy is collapsing?
And what should you do?
And I'm going to stop at points and I'm going to ask those questions.
And when I do that,
I would like you to think,
what would I do if that was me?
And with regards to the second of those questions,
what do you do when the economy is collapsing?
All of you will have a perspective on that
because you all live in a collapsing economy
and you're all doing something.
But this kind of economic collapse,
which is in my opinion,
a collapse caused by inequality,
it's a collapse which looks very, very different
depending on which angle you view it from.
So some of you will have been in the situations I've been in
and some of you won't have been.
But I want you to take it as an opportunity
to imagine you're in a different seat to where you are now
and ask yourself, honestly, what would I do if that was me?
Okay, so with that, I'm going to start,
I don't really like reading from speeches,
but I've written a little story.
When I was writing,
I wanted to start with my period of poverty,
which lasted about 20 years.
And I wrote a little bit about Ilford,
which is my hometown,
so I'm going to read it to you.
I'm going to have to change this first line
because there's a swear word in it.
I grew up in Ilford.
It's a bit of a slum,
but it's my slum.
Ilford is kind of a contested borderland war zone
between East London and Essex.
Everyone is from Pakistan or India or Sri Lanka or something,
but everyone talks in a half-Cockney accent.
When I was a teenager,
I used to sing songs in Punjabi
for illegal immigrants working in halal fried chicken shops
at 2am in the morning
for free chicken.
What do you want me to tell you?
I loved it.
I still do.
I miss it.
Ilford is one of the cheapest places to live in all of London.
I used to live in this tiny, narrow terraced house
on a street full of tiny, narrow terraced houses,
tucked in behind the high street.
It had three bedrooms.
It used to have two bedrooms,
but somebody had moved the bathroom
downstairs into the kitchen,
which meant that they could turn the old bathroom
upstairs into another bedroom.
And that's where I grew up,
in a bunk bed with my brother,
in a bunk bed in an old converted bathroom.
The train tracks that carried brokers and traders
in fast trains from out in Essex
down into the city
used to run right through my garden,
right past my bedroom window.
And when the fast trains came through,
the whole house used to shake.
But I never noticed.
When you grow up in a house
that gets shaken by a fast train
every four minutes,
you don't even notice
when a train shakes your house.
I was 12 or 13 the first time I noticed.
My friend from school came around
and he said,
damn, your whole house is shaking.
And that was the first time I realised.
What does that mean?
So I was in the bottom bunk
of that bunk bed when I was a kid.
And underneath my bed,
there was a single drawer
that had been removed
from a chest of drawers,
which had probably been destroyed long ago.
And in that single drawer,
I kept all of my worldly possessions.
I'll be honest,
it wasn't a particularly safe house
when I was a kid.
There was danger
and there was violence sometimes.
But, you know,
I was a kid.
What do you do?
And there are a lot of institutions
in our society
that are supposed to protect poor kids
and kids who are not safe.
There's the government,
the welfare state,
charity, philanthropy,
some religious institutions.
All I can tell you is,
I don't remember none of them coming for me.
So, you know,
what do you do?
There wasn't any help
as far as I can remember it
when I was a kid.
But there was a story.
A story is something to hold on to.
You work hard.
You kill all of your exams.
You destroy the competition.
Your friends,
of course.
You beat all your friends
into the top university.
This university.
And then you get
a whole load of new friends.
And you beat those new friends, too,
into the best job.
And then you get the best job
working for a bank in the city.
I didn't really know
what that meant,
to be honest.
But I had an image.
It was an image
of a large corner office
high up in a skyscraper somewhere
with carpeted floors
and windows for walls
and a high blue sky
and a warm sun
and views for miles
in every direction.
I don't actually know
if offices like that
really exist.
I never worked in one.
But, you know,
that was a story.
I've got to be honest,
I didn't really work hard.
There wasn't anywhere
to work in my house.
The only desk
in the whole house
was this little kind of
bureau thing
that you had to fold out
right next to my dad's bed
and when you did,
a whole load of moths
threw at you.
It was so dark
and musty there
that I don't think
anyone could work there.
But my parents
had a solution.
They got this, like,
plank of wood
and if you sat on the armchair
you could put the plank
of wood across.
And you could balance
your books
and you could write there.
But I didn't really like
doing that
because the plank
wasn't that long
and it would fall
and your books
would fall on the floor.
So I just went down
to the floor with them
and I put the plank
down on the floor
and I used to work there.
Lying down on my belly
in the middle of the front room
doing my maths homework
and my French homework
as my dad used to watch
Coronation Street
and my brother and sister
used to run around
screaming
and causing carnage.
What do you do, you know?
I didn't work hard.
Instead, I was out
on the streets.
You know, my street
was like a little
dead-end street
tucked in between
the high street
and the railway
and on one end
there was this old
abandoned factory
we used to play in
and on the other end
there was this
recycling centre
which had these huge
three metre high
piles of old newspapers.
We used to play
on them as well.
But there was never
any traffic on that street
and the kids used to
just play out every day.
And when the first
Canary Wharf skyscrapers
went up
which was happening
when I was about
nine or ten
we could see those
skyscrapers go up
in the distance.
And so I thought
that's it then.
That's where I'm
going to be.
Looks like a lot of
corner offices
in that building.
Maybe some other
kids thought the same.
But you know
I wasn't really studying.
But you might think
that's a problem
but to be honest
it weren't.
Because even though
I weren't never studying
I still came first
in every exam.
And I don't know why.
I don't know
what that means.
And the kids at school
would say
oh we know you're studying
and I would say
I'm not.
I'm not studying.
And they would say
we know that you are
and I don't know
what you say to that.
So I used to take
them sometimes
back to see my house.
The house used to
shake with the trains.
And then they knew
that I wasn't studying.
Because I wasn't.
Not long after that
I got expelled from school.
See I managed to get
into some fancy grammar school
and the kids there
knew that I could get drugs.
And they were right
I could get drugs.
There were drugs
on my street.
There was about
ten houses
I could have knocked on
at any time.
And those front doors
would open up
and they'd sell me drugs.
And those kids
at the grammar school
from fancy homes
and fancy houses
and staircases
that split in two
in the middle.
They didn't have doors
that opened up
like that on their streets.
But what they did have
was money.
Money.
So they brought
their money
that I didn't have
and I brought my drugs
which they didn't have.
And we met then
in bounteous free commerce.
And it wasn't them
it was me
that got expelled.
Wasn't it?
And I didn't know
quite what that meant.
What would you do?
You know
when I was very young
primary school
I had a school trip
to the seaside.
At that time
I owned
two pairs of shoes.
One was a pair
of black school shoes
that were a hand-me-down
for my older brother.
I wore those
to school
and to church.
I also had
one pair
of black
plimsoes.
Also
a hand-me-down
for my brother.
I wore those
for everything else.
That day
on the seaside
I took off
my plimsoes
and I ran
into the sea
and I played
in the waves.
And when I came
back to the shore
the plimsoes
were gone.
I guess the waves
must have taken them.
After that
I wore the black
school shoes
for everything.
PE class
everything.
I wore them
until they fell apart.
I don't know
you know.
What would you do?
And now this brings us
to our first
moral question.
At this point
we see
in sharp
moral focus
the meaning
of what it is
to be poor
and to try
to be rich.
So imagine this.
You are there
for the first day
of your new life.
You're 16.
You've just been
expelled from school.
In the night time
you were awoken
by your mother
crying at the foot
of your bed.
But she's gone now.
Everyone's gone now.
Your mum
and your dad
and your brother
are at work.
Your younger sister
she's still in school.
There's no one
in the house
and there's no school
to go to.
So you get out of bed
and you go downstairs
to the bathroom
which is in the kitchen
and you plug a little
plastic hose
into the taps
of the bathtub
and you sit down
on the cold plastic
and you shower yourself
and you watch the water
go down the drain
and you say to yourself
that's your life
that is.
That's your life.
And then you get out
of the bath
and you dry yourself
and you're drying your hair
and the doorbell rings
and it's your friend
from the street
who you've been smoking with
for about six months now
and he knows
that you've been expelled
from school
and he's really sorry
and he says
we should go and smoke up.
So now
what do you do?
This is the moment
when you realise
that to be poor
and to want to be rich
is a walking away.
It is a walking away
from the friends
you grew up with.
It is a walking away
from people like you.
And you know
deep within yourself
in your heart of hearts
these friends won't be okay
without you.
But what about you?
If you stick around
to save him
then who sticks around
to save you?
What does it mean
to be selfish?
What would you do
if it were you?
What would you do?
I didn't go.
I worked.
I worked there
by myself
in that cold
empty house
belly down
in the centre
of the front room.
Maths homework
chemistry homework
English homework
every day
on that small wooden board
and I did it
I killed my exams
I decimated the opposition
I outcompeted my friends
I won
then
my first taste of blood
so what next?
Three years later
the London School
of Economics
money
so I'll be honest
I thought LSE
was going to be difficult
but to be honest
it wasn't that hard
millionaires' kids
Gaddafi's kids
paying tens of thousands
of pounds
to send their kids
over to London
from all over the world
to get beat by me
in their exams
I don't know why
to be honest
I don't really know
what that means
but I had a desk then
not at home
there was a desk
in the library
so now you're at LSE
you're 19 years old
you're studying
maths and economics
which is basically
the same as economics
because economics
is mostly maths nowadays
your focus now
is on smashing
the other students
killing them
in their exams
making it clear
to everyone
that you are
the best student
in the union
and beating everyone
to the top job
that will make you
a millionaire
everyone else
is trying to do
the same thing
nobody's really
that bothered
in trying to work
out how the economy
works
why would we be
we didn't go there
to do that
we were there
to kill
to compete
to make money
it's not about knowledge
was that the right
thing to do
should you spend
your time
actually trying
to understand
the economy
and let everyone
else beat you
in your exams
then you'll never
be able to get
a job
to actually do
anything
with that knowledge
what would you do
now I made my decision
pretty quickly
and I killed
everyone in the
first year exams
I thought that was
the right path
to getting me
a millionaire job
but it turns out
it wasn't
because whilst grades
are important
to getting the top
jobs nowadays
other things
are more important
the actual way
you get a good job
nowadays
is sending a CV
and cover letter
so what do you put
on your CV
and cover letter
when you're 19
years old
you've been expelled
from school
for selling drugs
you did a paper
round for six years
you spent three years
fluffing pillows
in a sofa shop
in Bexford
next to a sewage
work
you spent a year
and a half
trying to become
a grime MC
my friend was head
of the duty
United Nations
my other friend
played oboe
at the Royal Albert Hall
he founded a charity
that runs
dirt bike tours
through the Sahara Desert
for some reason
why were their CV
so much better
than mine
they were better
because they knew
more likely
their parents
had known
they had known
that the day would come
when the children
of this world
would be divided
based on who
and who could not
play the oboe
so they made sure
that their kids
had oboes
and that's how jobs
are allocated
in this world
it's not by exams
I see that now
what does that mean
what do you do
okay so you need
to find a new route
you need to sneak in
through the back door
despite the fact
that your grades
are the best
in the whole university
you look for a back door
and you find one
competition
a card game
one bank runs
across five universities
in the country
the winner
of the whole competition
gets an internship
a game
sounds nice
sounds fair
doesn't it
sounds like you don't
need to play the oboe
at least
but it's risky
isn't it
it's a game
so what you do
you do some research
and you manage to find out
the rules of the game
before the competition itself
then when you walk
into the competition
against the other wealthy
economic students
you win
at least partially
because you had an advantage
an unfair advantage
you cheated
in a sense
to win
what does that mean
you cheated
to win a game
that you needed
to win
in order to get a job
despite being
one of the top students
in the whole university
what does that mean
is that fair
is that human
what would you do
okay so now you get the job
now you're a trader
the best job
in the world
there's no corner office
it's a big room
it's the job everybody wanted
you get to the trading floor
of one of the world's biggest banks
and it's full of genius millionaires
except it's not really is it
it's full of men with nice shirts
expensive haircuts
it's kind of full of obvious psychopaths
with emotional problems
and people who shout a lot
and aren't really that smart
and you suppose that
that should have been obvious really
because it's full of the same people
you studied with at LSE
and they were never really chosen
because they were smart
they were chosen
because their dads were rich
what does that mean
so you're there now
you're young
and you're hungry
and you're there to make money
and you want to learn from someone
you want to learn how to trade
how to make money
but everyone there is kind of insane
and then suddenly
it's October 2008
and the world blows up
and Lehman goes bankrupt
and seven of your friends
who studied with you
at the London School of Economics
and had only just started working there
lose their jobs
and TV cameras go down to their office
which is just down the road from your office
and your friends pack all their personal possessions
into little green Lehman Brothers duffel bags
that they'd received just a couple weeks earlier
as a welcome gift
for managing to get one of the best jobs
in the entire world
and they carry those little green duffel bags
and cardboard boxes
full of their possessions
down into taxis
down to the station
and TV cameras film them
and you see them
on TV
and you feel bad for them
because you know them
because you study with them
but you don't feel bad for them really
because you know
they should have chosen better
when they got randomly assigned a bank
just like you
what does that mean?
what would you do?
and everyone around you starts to make money
two traders in my team of traders
made 100 million dollars in profit
the year Lehman went under
so what do you do?
y'all know what I did
I started to copy them
even though I had no idea
what any of them were doing
and the next year
I made 12 million dollars in profit
but that year there was a lot of public discontent
about the pay and the bankers bonuses
the bankers who in their eyes
had ruined the global economy
and I sat there on the trading floor
and I was still a poor boy
sleeping on broken mattresses
still showering with a hose in my parents' bathtub
only now surrounded by millionaires
as Gordon Brown
the then Prime Minister of my country
said he would tax the bankers
he would tax their bonuses
and I looked around
and the millionaires around me
were laughing
and one of them grabbed my shoulder
and he said
don't worry Gary
they'll never tax us
and I took a big breath in
and I breathed it all out
what does that mean?
what would you do?
I waited for my first big bonus
I was expecting it to be 100,000 pounds
at that time in my life
100,000 pounds was the biggest sum of money
that I could imagine
my dad had worked his whole life
for 20,000 pounds a year
what I got
was 395,000 pounds
what does that mean?
what would you do?
you know when I was in sixth form
I would skip lunch to save money
my friend Asad
would sometimes feel bad for me
and he'd buy me a burger meal
from a shop called Pizza King
around the corner from the school
and I'd have it with burger sauce
you know that orange sauce
when I was at uni for lunch
I would buy two scotch eggs from Tesco
for 75p
every day for two years
and then one day
when I had just turned 23
someone gave me 395,000 pounds
what does that mean?
what would you do?
I wanted more
the next year, 2010
I copied everyone again
and it didn't work
for the first time ever
I lost money
I lost 8 million dollars
in one single week
when the Swiss National Bank
unexpectedly cut its interest rates
to negative 4.5%
that was the first time ever
that it occurred to me
that maybe LSE had done me a disservice
maybe memorising answers
and not actually learning anything
wasn't really that useful
maybe you did need to know
about the economy after all
who knew?
but that moment began an obsession
for me
an obsession that continues today
an obsession to understand the economy
why did I want to understand the economy?
because I wanted to make money
what does that mean?
what would you do?
so around about that time
late 2010
early 2011
I was starting to understand
that nobody had any idea
what they were doing
see my job was to predict interest rates
to summarise quite aggressively
interest rates go down
when the economy is weak
and up when the economy is strong
by the beginning of 2011
I had witnessed markets
predict interest rates
completely incorrectly
for three years
see cutting interest rates to zero
is supposed to stimulate the economy
that's what we are taught at university
due to the massive interest rate cuts in 2008
economists all expected the economy
to bounce back sharply in 2009
it didn't
after that
economists expected the same thing
to happen in 2010
it didn't
I didn't know at the time
but this pattern would actually continue
for 13 years
economists in the UK
predicted economic and interest rate recovery
every single year
from 2009 to 2020
in 2020
they finally agreed
that interest rates would actually
never go up again
what does that mean?
anyway look
I didn't know this at that time
all I knew then
was that the traders
and the economists
have been wrong for three years
they were predicting economic recoveries
that won't happen
why?
in my opinion
the reason those traders
and economists
thought the economy would get better
every single year
from 2008 up to now
is because for them
it did get better
for the rich
life got better
and better
pretty much every single year
from 2008 up to now
so why did interest rates stay at zero
that whole decade
after 2010
I had an idea
the reason interest rates
are supposed to stimulate the economy
is because they're supposed to get you spending
but people weren't spending
and I asked a few of the traders
why
and they said
you know
there's problems with the banking sector
which are fixed now
there's problems with confidence
that are fixed now
one time I asked an Oxford economics professor
why did you think
spending was so weak
after 2008?
he said
there was an exogenous shock
to consumption savings preferences
so I decided
to do something radical
in the world of economics
I went out
and I started asking people
have you had an exogenous shock
to your consumption savings preferences
I'm going to read you a passage
from my book
because my publicist will be delighted
this is what people said
when I asked them
why they weren't spending more money
I asked Harry Sambi
Harry was still just a kid
Harry had holes in his shoes
and he was jumping over the barriers
on the tube
to save costs
that's why he didn't spend money
I asked Asad
Asad said his mum
had sold the family home
to support him and his sisters
and now he was sleeping on the sofa
to try and save up a deposit
that's why they didn't spend money
I asked Aidan
Aidan's mum had lost her job
and hadn't been able to get a new rate
on the mortgage
now the monthly payments were sky high
and Aidan was having to pay them himself
that's why they didn't spend money
they were losing their homes
I hadn't even noticed
so you realise
that the hundreds of billions of pounds
the importance of the economy
by governments and central banks
aren't doing anything
to protect ordinary people
very shortly after that
you recognise that basically
every government
in the world
is bankrupt
Spain
Italy
Portugal
Greece
but also the UK
the US
Japan
at that time
early 2011
all of these governments
had massive deficits
that were growing
they were selling off their assets
they were going into debt
they were losing their homes
but if the government
is losing
its assets
and going into debt
and the people
are losing their assets
and going into debt
then where are the assets going
and who's on the other side
of the debt
then I looked to the right of me
and I looked to the left of me
and I realised I was surrounded
by millionaires
it was us
wasn't it
we were the balance
we were the boys
who would be richer
than our fathers
in a world full of kids
who'd be poor
it was us
we were the ones
on the other side
of the Italian government debt
we were the ones
on the other side
of Aidan's mum's mortgage
we would buy Assad's mum's house
and rent it back
to Assad's kids
and then we would have the house
and the debt too
we'd lend it back to them
and it would grow
and it would compound
the situation wouldn't get better
it would get worse
it wasn't confidence
it was cancer
it was never going to get better
what does that mean?
I knew what it meant
it meant I had to buy
a green euro dollar futures
now that's the bet on interest rates
at that time
everybody thought interest rates
would go up
but they wouldn't
I put that bet on a massive size
and by the end of the year
I was Citibank's most profitable
trader in the world
and Citibank paid me
two million dollars
and said well done mate
do it again
and what does that mean?
what would you do?
I did it one more year
I am not going to lie to you
the next year
I was sitting at my desk
and I said to one of the young traders
who I worked with
do you think we should do something?
he said to me
what do you mean?
I said
do you think we should do something
about the collapsing economy
he said
what do you mean?
I said
do you think we should do something?
he said
we bought
we bought the green euro dollars
what do you want?
I said to him
I don't think this is about
the green euro dollars
do you think we should do something
about the collapsing economy?
he said to me
sorry I don't understand
what do you mean?
I tried to explain to him
that maybe we
as wealthy people
have an understanding
of the problematic economy
should do something
to make it better
he said to me
Gary
that's impossible
and I knew of course
that he was right
but for some reason
I quit my job anyway
and I would love to tell you
it's because I'm a good person
because I'm a nice guy
but the truth is
it's because I was sick
I wanted to sit there
and make more money
but I was losing weight
every single day
I'd bought a new luxury apartment
and I'd ripped all of the furnishings out
for some reason
I couldn't buy more
and I used to sleep
on a mattress
on a bare concrete floor
with white plaster walls
and every day
I'd trade a trillion dollars
and be Citibank's
most profitable trader
in the world
and what does that mean?
I quit that job
and if you want to hear
the story of that
it's in the book
but I want to talk about
what happened afterwards
because first I tried to
work for a think tank
and I made a website
called Wealth Economics
it's still up
you can look at it if you want
explaining that
if you don't fix
wealth inequality
the economy will collapse
this theory made me
millions of dollars
nobody looked at the website
you can still look at it
if you want
but of course nobody's
going to look at the website
nobody knows who you are
so what do you do
so you go back to university
you go back to university
you go to Oxford
best university in the world
contentious
and you go to your first
lecture on interest rates
and at this point
you've just stopped being
the world's most profitable
interest rates trader
and you go to the lecture
and you say
hey
can we talk about
why we've been so wrong
about interest rates
for the past 10 years
and he says to you
oh we always knew
interest rates would stay zero
what does that mean
and you say to him
no you didn't
you predicted it wrong
for 10 years in a row
and he says
no we knew
we knew
and you say to him
okay well I'll go home
and I'll send you the data
and he says
oh yeah
you're right
you were wrong for 10 years
and it don't go no further
what does that mean
and you go to your
mid-year review
and you sit there
with your college professors
and they ask you
what do you think
of the course
you tell them
it's not very good
maybe you use
some stronger words
I've been asked
not to swear
in this lecture
and they say
why don't you like it
and I say
why don't you talk
about people's economic problems
and they turn around
to you and they say
what do you mean
the economy is good
and you sit there
with these three men
in capes
in this wood paneled hall
and you hear
these two unspoken words
reverberate back
from the walls
it's good
for us
what does that mean
so you decide
you have to leave university
and you have to try
and do something
more active
you have to go out
and you have to speak
to people directly
you have to tell them
if things don't get better
if there's no action
in equality
that their lives
are going to get worse
and worse
then immediately
there's a pandemic
and the government
gives out 800 billion pounds
and you can see
from the analysis
right at the beginning
that that money
will be accumulated
by the rich
and nobody
at the universities
in the opposition party
in the government
in the civil service
in the central banks
even ask the question
of who's going to
accumulate this 800 billion dollar
so you put a massive bet
on increasing asset prices
and you make 300,000 pounds
what does that mean
but you also make
a YouTube channel
when you try
and tell people
this is going to happen
you write in the Guardian
that there's going to be
a massive crisis
of inequality
falling in living standards
at the same time
Larry Elliott
chief economics correspondent
of the Guardian
predicts that house prices
will collapse
three years later
you were right
and Larry Elliott
was wrong
but obviously
nobody remembers
what does that mean
and you work
and eventually
you manage to
build up a following
you put up videos
every week
and people turn around
to you and say
there's no point
there's nothing
you can do
there's no way
to stop it
so what do you do
I want to speak to you
about an event
that I spoke at
it was at Saatchi
I probably can't mention
it was at a fancy
advertising company
you can edit that out
right
and I sat on the stage
and I told them
in a much shorter version
what I just told you
that the economy
will collapse
and it will get worse
and worse
I'm not just saying
that I'm betting on it
I make hundreds of thousands
of pounds on it
every year
I've made millions
of pounds on it
in my life
and the woman next to you
who by all accounts
seems like a very nice woman
says what gives me hope
is that the economy
is like nature
sometimes it gets better
and sometimes it gets worse
and what I heard
when she said that was
my life's comfortable
I ain't gonna do nothing
and you start thinking
it's impossible isn't it
because the poor
are struggling
to put food on the table
you expect them
to stand up
and defend themselves
and the rich
have got kitchen
renovations to worry about
so they're too busy
to help
the problem is
people are inherently
selfish
maybe there's no way out
maybe this is just
inevitable
it's the way they work
in society
and then I got sent
to do a story
in Colburn
which is
in northern Yorkshire
it was about
how Rishi Sunak
is the richest MP ever
and I was gonna go
to a food bank
and I was gonna ask them
how do you feel
about having the richest
ever MP
in history
and just coincidentally
it happened
that Russia invaded Ukraine
the previous weekend
before I ran up there
and the food bank
that I was visiting
had been converted
into a place
to sort the donations
that were gonna be sent
to Ukraine
and it was full of people
sorting clothes
and medicine
and food
into different bin bags
and there were three guys
there with vans
that were gonna drive
the stuff
all the way there
to Ukraine himself
and I started asking
the people
you know
like
who are these people
doing this
and you find out
it's the users
of the food bank
and maybe people
are inherently selfish
after all
there's a story
in the bible
it's called
the widow's mite
and it talks about
all the people
who give money
extravagantly
to charity
to religion
and it talks about
one widow
who just put
two small copper coins
in the box
and apparently
I never met him
Jesus said
she's given more
than everybody else
for all these
have of their abundance
cast in
unto the offerings
of God
but she of her penury
have cast in
all the living
that she had
maybe people
are inherently selfish
I don't know
what do you do
I wanted to read
a little bit
from a book
that I like
it's by an author
called Camus
this book
is called
the plague
and he talks
about what people
do in a society
that is collapsing
apparently it's
about the Nazis
but I didn't know
that because
it's a metaphor
or something
and what he says
is that basically
when society collapses
most people go crazy
but some people don't
and there's a group
of people that
started trying
to fight
the plague
Camus says
Taru started work
the very next day
and mustered
a first team
that was to be
followed by many others
however
it is not the narrator's
intention
to attribute
more significance
to these health groups
than they actually have
it is true
that nowadays
many of our fellow citizens
would
in his place
succumb to the temptation
to exaggerate their role
but the narrator
is rather inclined
to believe
that by giving
too much importance
to fine actions
one may end
by paying an indirect
but powerful tribute
to evil
because in so doing
one implies
that such fine actions
are only valuable
because they are rare
and that malice
or indifference
are far more common
motives
in the actions of men
the narrator
does not share this view
the evil in the world
comes almost always
from ignorance
and goodwill
can cause as much damage
as ill will
if it is not enlightened
Camus thinks
that when you are
in a society
that is collapsing
your job
is to stop it
from collapsing
Camus thinks
that's how you be human
but there are a lot
of people in this town
that don't agree
and he speaks about
this as well
in Camus words
a lot of new moralists
appeared in the town
at this moment
saying that nothing
was any use
and that we should
go down on our knees
Taru, Ryu
and their friends
could answer this or that
but the conclusion
was always what they knew
it would be
one must fight
in one way or another
and not go down
on one's knees
I found that very moving
when I read that
in Camus' story
most people
when society collapses
go crazy
they become extremely
religious
or they become
extremely
hedonistic
or they become
extremely greedy
and they try to make money
they become really angry
and try to find people
to hate
and I think this is natural
you know
I think this is what happens
when society's collapse
and I don't think we can
blame people
for doing this
disaster is a hard thing
to face
and look I see
I see the madness
if you've got a social media
platform getting a thousand
comments every day
you see the madness
in society
I don't blame people
for falling into madness
some of you will fall
into madness too
maybe you already have done
into selfishness
into greed
into nihilism
but I can't blame you
it's very human
and society will tell you
you have a choice
in the face of disaster
to turn away
to tell yourself a story
that it's not real
that it's not going to happen
that it's only natural
the changing of the seasons
and if you do that
you can probably do
what you wanted to do
all along
you can be selfish
you can ignore it
you can get that kitchen renovation
and you can tell yourself
that the poverty
that is growing
in society
that the plague
that is infecting
everybody else
may never darken your door
and you don't have to do
what the biblical widow did
you don't have to give everything
in the face of chaos
you have a choice to make
right
you have to choose
either yourself
or others
you know
I worked in Japan
for a couple of years
and at that time
I lost my mind
I fell into a deep depression
and I spoke to my Japanese junior
and I told him
how watching these millionaires
obsess about money
as the world collapsed around them
made me sick
and how I couldn't eat
and how I couldn't sleep
that kid his name was Kosuke
and his English wasn't good
and he said to me
yes, yes, I understand
the problem is
these men
have very
small
hearts
you know
sometimes I wonder
why it's me up here
from a broken home
broken family
from poverty
struggling often
with my mental health
sometimes struggling
to get out of bed
every day
sometimes I wonder
where all the good kids are
all the nice kids
with the nice families
that go home
to lovely big houses
and have lovely meals
and lovely dining tables
where are they?
why is it me here?
what are we?
what are we as humans?
are we people who have to choose
between ourselves and others?
do our hearts have only room
for one of these ideas?
or can we be something more?
can we be bigger?
can we be people who care
not only for ourselves
our immediate families
us as individuals
but those around us
society as well
can we fit both of these things
into our hearts?
can we take what we need
but also
more than that
after that
find something left to
to give
even if it's only
two copper coins
I believe that we can
no
I don't believe that
I believe that we have to
if we don't
the whole thing will collapse
but to finish
I would like to answer the question
for me
and you will have your own opinions
what does it mean
to be human
in a time of disaster?
what does it mean
to be human
in a collapsing economy?
and me personally
I agree with Kami
the job of a human
in face of a disaster
is to try to prevent
that disaster
that's what I'll be trying to do
and I hope you'll try too
good luck
thank you
well Guy
that was sensational